A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Office Files of Robert S. Wickham FA570
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Office Files of Robert S. Wickham
1964-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wickham, Robert S.
Ford Foundation
FA570
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 Hollinger document boxes
The Population Program was created in 1963 to better facilitate research and more efficiently handle grant proposals pertaining to the health and welfare of communities in the United States and abroad. The Population program became a sub-division of the Foundation's International Division in 1966. In 1981, it again gained independent program status. Due to subsequent reorganizations the Population Program now falls under the purview of the Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights division of the Education, Creativity and Free Expression program. Robert Saunderson Wickham joined the Ford Foundation in 1956 as a staff associate for the South and Southeast Asia program. During his tenure at the Foundation, he served as a regional representative and a program director, and by his retirement had been promoted to Program Officer of the International Division's Population Office. This small collection of his papers contains materials from two conferences, the Foundation's Population Conference held in Lake Como, Italy in April 1968 and the Family Planning Evaluation Conference held in Marino, Italy from April 20-24, 1970. The files include agendas, published and unpublished papers, and discussion topics and notes from one session of the Foundation's 1968 conference and materials from all twelve sessions of the 1970 conference.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
The collection contains one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Population and Family Planning Conferences, 1964-1970
Scope and Contents
This small collection of office files of Robert Wickham consists of materials from two conferences, the Foundation's Population Conference in Lake Como, Italy from April 8-11, 1968 and the Family Planning Evaluation Conference in Marino, Italy from April 20-24, 1970. The collection contains files from one session of the Foundation's 1968 conference and from all twelve sessions of the 1970 conference.
Reports written by Ford Foundation employees on reproductive health and population control form the bulk of the collection. They address the demographic effects of family planning programs, the awareness and use of contraceptives, the application of computer-generated surveys and software options for tabulating and monitoring family planning programs, and a myriad of fertility-related studies carried out in the United States and abroad.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Saunderson Wickham was born on May 11, 1925. Mr. Wickham joined the U.S. Army in 1943 and served until 1946. Following the end of World War II and his service in the Army, Mr. Wickham enrolled at Haverford College. In 1950, he graduated cum laude with a Bachelor of Arts in Political Science and as a member of the national honor society, Phi Beta Kappa. From 1950 to 1952, Mr. Wickham worked for the U.S. Department of the Interior as a management trainee and a foreign affairs analyst for the Division of International Activities. From 1952 to 1953, the U.S. Technical Cooperation Administration employed him as chief of their training branch and as a program and budget officer for activities in Tehran, Iran. From 1954 through the spring of 1956, Mr. Wickham was involved in highly classified work for the U.S. government.
Mr. Wickham joined the Ford Foundation's Overseas Development Division as a staff associate for the South and Southeast Asia region in April 1956. In October 1957, he transitioned into the role of Program Assistant for the Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC) region. From 1958 to 1959, Mr. Wickham attended Harvard University's Kennedy School of Government where he earned a Master of Public Administration in economic development and, in October 1960, received a promotion to Program Associate of LAC. He became the Foundation's representative to Colombia, Venezuela, and Peru in September 1962, and in May 1965 his responsibilities expanded when he became Representative of Mexico, all of Central America, and Venezuela. The following year, in October 1966, Mr. Wickham rose to Associate Director of Latin America and the Caribbean, and, in September 1968, became the Program Officer for the Latin American region. Mr. Wickham transferred to the International Division's Population Office as its Program Officer in August 1971.
Mr. Wickham retired from the Foundation on June 27, 1983 and moved to Santa Fe, New Mexico.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Population Program was created in 1963 to provide improved support for research and to more efficiently handle grant proposals pertaining to the health and welfare of communities in the United States and abroad. In 1966, the Population program became a sub-division of the Foundation's International Division and remained so until 1981 when it again gained independent program status. Following a reorganization of the Foundation in 1992, the newly formed Reproductive Health and Population program absorbed the existing Population program. The ASSETS program (Asset Building and Community Development Program) was introduced in 1997 and included a subdivision focused on Human Development and Reproductive Health. Though the Human Development and Reproductive Health program was canceled in 2002, the Education, Creativity and Free Expression program restored the Foundation's work in population health in 2009 with the creation of a subdivision focused on Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Population and Family Planning Conferences, 1964-1970; I
  Scope and Contents
  The records of the two conferences comprise this series and contain agendas, a list of attendees, unpublished background and position papers, published articles, and discussion topics provided to participants of both the 1968 Population Conference and the 1970 Family Planning Evaluation Conference.
  - 1968 Family Planning Conference (1 of 2), 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1968 Family Planning Conference (2 of 2) (reports separated), 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Sessions 1, 2, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 3, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 4, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 5, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 6, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 7 (folder 1 of 4), 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 7 (folder 2 of 4), 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 7 (folder 3 of 4), 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 7 (folder 4 of 4), 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 8, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 9 (folder 1 of 2), 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 9 (folder 2 of 2), 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 10 (folder 1 of 2), 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Session 10 (folder 2 of 2), 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Marino Family Planning Evaluation Conference (April 1970) -- Sessions 11, 12, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)